hello everybody and welcome to part five
大家好，欢迎收看
in this GMOD LUA a tutorial series
GMOD LUA系列教程第五期
now before we get started I do want to
在开始之前先向各位
apologize for the lack of videos I have
诚恳道歉，最近更新的并不勤快
not been feeling too well my mixer broke
我感觉很不好，因为我的混音器坏了
meaning of my mic quality was just
这意味着我的麦克风音质
appalling and again I really really
会非常差，我非常非常
apologize for it but nevertheless let's
抱歉，不过还是
get started so in this video we're gonna
让我们开始吧。在这期视频里
be taking a look at running functions on
我们要在玩家身上
the player which is important for two
运行一些函数，有两个原因使得这件事很重要
reasons one is because we need to
其中之一是我们需要
understand how we can execute Meta
去理解怎样在不同的数据类型上
functions on different data types but on
执行meta函数
top of that we also need to understand
除此以外我们也需要理解
how we can get references to players in
怎样在不同的情况下获得对玩家的引用
different situations so what we're gonna
我们要做的是
do we're gonna stop a single player
开启单人游戏
world if you have not done so already I
如果你还没打开的话
recommend you do so now then what we're
我建议你赶紧跟上，然后
gonna do is we're gonna open up sublime
我们打开sublime（你自己的编辑器也可以）
and that Lua file that is in our Garry's
然后打开之前那期视频的lua文件，它保存在
Mod directory if you guys remember it
我们GMOD主目录的lua文件夹下
from the previous video I think so
如果你们还记得的话
anyway we're gonna go ahead we're gonna
总之让我们继续
get rid of that and we're gonna get
不谈前面的了，我们现在就开始
started so if you remember before well
(又是一段废话)
actually we're get started first how do
首先，我们怎样
we get a reference to the player so I'm
去获取一个玩家的引用呢
gonna open up the gmod wiki and I'm
首先我会打开GMOD WIKI
gonna go ahead and search local whoops
然后搜索local，哦
Localplayer and as you can see on the
Localplayer，然后你可以看到
global there's a function here called
在global底下有个函数
Localplayer now you know it's it's
叫LocalPlayer()，注意到
orange which means you can only run on
这个函数是橙色的，意味着你只能在
the client and the description says that
客户端执行这个函数，描述中说这个函数
it returns to place object of the
它会返回执行函数的当前客户端对应的
current client localplayer will return
玩家对象，并且这个函数在
null until all entities have been
所有实体都被初始化以前，只会返回空(NULL)
initialized so this part we don't need
在这一期里我们倒是不用
to worry about for now but this part is
担心这个，上面这句话更重要的
important it returns to players object
这个函数能返回玩家对象
yet the player object of the current
yes,执行函数的客户端对应的玩家对象
client so what that means is it will
这意味着
return the player object itself in the
它能够返回游戏世界里的
physical world and then we can do
玩家本体，我们可以借此
whatever we want to it so what we're
对玩家做出一系列我们想做的操作，我们现在
gonna do is I'm gonna make a local
创建一个本地变量
variable call it ply and I'm gonna set
叫做ply，令它等于
it equal to Localplayer() and I'm gonna
LocalPlayer()
call that and I do have to call it as a
注意后面要加上()，因为这是唤起一个函数
function let me go ahead and change this
注意把GMOD
to GMOD there we go I do have to set
语法高亮打开
as a function because that's what it is
(再次废话一下这个是函数，要加())
and now the variable PR y then source of
现在ply就成了
reference to this so just a just a
对玩家的一个引用
double check I'm gonna do lua_
然后我们再检测一下，打开控制台输入lua_
whoops lua_openscript_cl
哦,lua_openscript_cl
now you're gonna want to make
注意了请确保你
sure that you run this on the client
是在客户端运行的(要加_cl)
because local player will not work on
因为localplayer()这个函数
the server as we've seen it's a client
不能再服务端执行，我们之前看到了它是个
only function so when we run this as you
只能在客户端运行的函数，接着我们运行
can see we've got no errors so things
你会发现没有任何错误
are good
这很好
what can we do with this well let's go
然后我们能用它来做什么呢？
ahead and go back to the gmod wiki and
让我们回到GMOD WIKI，然后
search player if you search whoopsie
搜索player:,哦，是player
player right and then we're gonna go
然后我们可以
into the classes section here and you'll
点击到classuanxiangka1，然后你能看到
see all of these player : and then a ton
这一系列以Player:(注意冒号)开头的
of these functions right so let's go
一大堆函数(译者注:或者说Player类的方法)，让我们
have a look at alive now this is blue
看一个这个Player:Alive函数函数，这个函数被
and orange which means it can be used on
标记为蓝色和橙色，意味着
both client and server now it checks if
服务端和客户端都能执行它，它的作用是检测
the player is alive and will return a
一个玩家是否还活着，并返回一个
boolean which is true or false of
Boolean类型的结果，值为true(真)或false(假)
whether the player is alive or not so
表示对应的玩家是活着或似了
now let's say we go back in here we're
让我们回到我们的脚本，我们
gonna go ahead and print well first of
继续另起一行，写下print，哦我们首先
all we're gonna make available I'm gonna
还是新建一个变量，我给它命名为
call it isPlayerAlive now the way
isPlayerAlive，我们唤起
how we call these functions is kind of
这个函数的方式
exactly what they look like here player
就像wiki上写的那样，把冒号前的
would be our reference to the player
Player，换成你想要检测的玩家的引用
then we do : and we call the function on
然后写下冒号，再写下函数名Alive()对玩家
the player so in this case we can do
执行函数，在我们这个脚本里，我们要写
ply:Alive() now remember that PR y is our
ply:Alive()，请记住，ply是我们获取到的
reference to our local player and what
对客户端本地玩家的一个引用
we're gonna do is we're gonna check if
我们要做的是检测
it's alive we're gonna store the value
他是否还活着，并把返回的结果
that it returns inside of this is player
存储到isPlayerAlive变量里
alive
----------
and we're simply gonna go ahead and
我们就这样继续
we're gonna print out isPlayerAlive I
然后把isPlayerAlive这个变量
do apologize for that couch in let me
打印出来，哦不好意思手滑了
zoom out a bit hey guys so now if I go
我把界面缩小一下，好现在
back into my game and I run the script
我调回游戏界面，再次执行这个脚本
as you can see it prints out true but if
你可以看到控制台打印了true
I go ahead and kill myself and I rerun
但是如果我把自己处似之后再次执行脚本
that's good it now prints out false
对了，打印出来的是false
because I am no longer alive so I hope
因为我现在挂了，我希望你理解
you understand that but on top of that
不过除此以外
there is many many many things we can do
我们还可以做很多很多很多事情
and in case you didn't notice at the
别忘了wiki上
wiki there is a lot of things here so
还有好多东西呢
let's go ahead and look at a few other
我们继续去看一看其他的函数吧
one so now the one set of blue for
比如这个蓝色的
example kill kill can only be called as
kill函数，kill函数只能被
it says here can only be called because
就像这蓝色表明的，它只能
it's blue on the server which means that
被服务端唤起，这意味着
on the client you cannot kill anybody
在客户端，你不能强制处似任何人
from the client you can ask the server
从客户端你只能去向服务端发送请求
to kill people but we'll get into that
去处似某人，不过这个机制我们会在
on another date so let's go ahead and
之后的节目里讲到，现在我们要做的是
take a look at some more some of these
让我们继续看看其他的
being like the orange one we can take a
带橙色的函数，比如
look at is speaking
这个IsSpeaking函数
and that is gonna return true or false of
它会返回一个true或false的boolean
whether the play was speaking we got set
表示这个玩家是否在开麦克风
muted which would mute a never player on
我们再看看这个setmuted函数，这个函数能在服务端上
the server so as long as you had this
让特定玩家封麦，只要你有...
would be the the other play on the
呃，也可以让其他玩家封麦，只要你有
server then you could have a reference
那个玩家对象的引用就行
to them set them to meet it and set to
然后你就可以对他执行setmute函数，并
meet it to true but yeah we're gonna go
传递一个true参数，我们接着看看
ahead and take a look at frags
Frags这个函数
so basically frags is kills and as you
基本上来说frags就是打敌数，正如你看到的
can see my frags right now is going to
我的frags应该是
be zero because on the scoreboard wait
0，因为计分板上。。。等等
my frag is negative one actually because
我的frag是-1，因为我
I killed myself but we'll go ahead and
刚刚击败自己了一次，我们继续
we'll store frags in there instead of
我们把frags存储在这里，然后
we'll just name this two kills and let's
把变量命名为kills,然后
go ahead and simply print that out now
继续把这个变量打印出来
let's go ahead and run our script and as
然后我们执行这个脚本
you can see it prints out negative one
你可以看到打印的结果是-1
but let's say I go to the NPC section
我们打开NPC选项卡
here and I just couldn't go to a weapon
然后我们切到武器选项卡
and grab something now all of these are
拿一把武器，然后我们把这些
obviously account if it kills and as you
NPC都图了，然后你可以看到
can see oops on the scoreboard I oh I
计分板上，哦不
guess not
我想的不对
I thought that the NPC's Count as kills
我以为击打NPC能够增加击打数
but clearly not so I'm still gonna be on
但显然不是这样，所以我还是
negative one but what we can do is we
\-1分，不过我们还可以
can also get my deaths now I know this
获取我的似亡数，我知道这看起来
may seem a bit repetitive but I'm just
有点无聊，但我还是
trying to make sure that you understand
想要确保你能理解
the point of this now as you can see
这一期视频的主旨
I've died once I do it again I've died
我之前似了一次，让我们再似一次
two times and I couldn't die again for
现在我似了两次，然后我还可以……
whoops I can die no I've got it there we
哦，我还可以，哦不
go
继续
I can die again for the third time now I
我现在似了三次(你可以看到脚本输出的也是3)
hope this makes sense but yeah and the
希望这些对你有用
actually will do it this video you guys
这期视频大概就到这里了
seem to like longer videos so we'll do
似乎你们更喜欢长一点的视频
this one so now we can do that actually
所以我就做的稍微长了些，还有一些内容
nest now I do I do apologize I will
我们下期再说吧，我很抱歉
leave that to the next video because it
把这些内容留到下期，否则
is gonna be a little longer but yeah I
这个视频就太长了
hope you guys learn something I hope you
希望你们能学到
understood some some stuff but yeah
并且理解这些内容
that's how we can execute information on
让我们复习一下，本期我们学习了处理
the player now retrieving a specific
玩家信息的方法，不过在服务端
player on the server is different which
检测玩家是不太一样的
is why we haven't gone into the server
这就是为什么这期没有做服务端的脚本
side yet but for the client you can get
不过在客户端你就能轻松
the the client player which is the the
获取客户端对应的玩家
person's game who it is you can get
谁开着游戏执行了这个脚本，谁就是
their client their player
客户端对应的玩家
and we store it in the variable player
然后我们把它存储在玩家变量(ply)里
which is our reference to it and then we
这就建立了一个对该玩家的应用，接着
call on that variable the function depth
我们用这个变量呼叫函数Death()
which will return the number of deaths
它将会返回玩家的
that players had then we simply go ahead
似亡次数，获取到之后
and we print that out so I hope that
我们就直接答应出来
makes sense to you in the next video
希望这些对你有所帮助，下一期视频
we'll go ahead and we'll do a little bit
我们将会做一些
more complicated again and I do
更复杂的脚本
apologize for those of you who find this
我再次对觉得这个系列视频太简单的观众
series very simple it will grow very
说一声抱歉，因为视频内容
fine complexity but to begin with for
会逐渐变复杂，但对于新人来说
people who are new they've got to
在视频的开头，最好还是
understand these basics and and even
讲清楚最基础的内容
though you may think I'm never gonna use
尽管你可能觉得这些内容我永远都不会用到
this in my script you will they are the
但这些内容是
fundamentals of coding for gmod so again
GMOD编程的重要基础，所以
I hope you learned something and I will
我希望你能从中学到一些东西
see you all in the next video hope you
我们下期视频再见，希望
enjoyed it
你看的愉快
you